at the time of this recording if you
typee in the word castor oil into a
search engine you'd think that castor
oil could cure you of just about any
disease especially by the uh natural
remedy sect of the health influencer
World anyway is there any scientific
truth to the claims at least in relation
to Eye Health does it help with your dry
eyes does it help get rid of eye
floaters does it help get rid of
cataracts and a key caveat that puts a
lot of this into perspective we'll
discuss as well we will find out but
this time I'm not alone because I'm
bringing in the big guns and I don't
mean my puny biceps rather a
collaboration with Dr Joseph Allen or as
you might know him Dr IH Health to help
make sense of the castor oil claims in
addition I'll do what I usually do add
the studies let's do it
first let's consult with Dr IH Health on
what castor oil even is what is castor
oil so castor oil is a seed oil from the
ricinus communis plant it's kind of
famous as having a high concentration of
rinic acid which works as a very potent
laxative in fact that's what it's FDA
approved for here in the United States
so be careful with that otherwise it is
also used as a component in various
moisturizers for things like skin care
hair care and even in small
concentrations in some eye drops yeah as
poignantly explained castor oil is used
for other purposes with its approval as
a laxative and as we all know what's
good for the rear end must be good for
the eyes
science a kid but when consumed castor
oil is enzymatically acted upon and
converted to what Dr Allen mentioned
rinic acid which interacts with your
intestinal cells and stimulates an
everyday process called Paralis
essentially it stimulates the intestines
to well get a move on it hence the you
know laxative effect anyway pertinent to
Eye
Health there are products that actually
do contain castor oil so does that mean
that it's effective well let's start
with understanding a bit on I Anatomy
because it'll help us get an idea of how
to think about some of these health
concerns so can I help you walk through
the anatomy of the eye so the anatomy of
the eye the front surface is actually
the tear film a lot of people don't
think about that but your tear are not
just water they're actually electrolytes
and proteins and this helps not only
focus light going from the air to the
eye but also helps keep the eyes moist
it also protects against pathogens and
anything that could be getting into the
eye behind that you have the cornea
which is most of the refractive power of
the eye is just in that front surface
and that's why we can do lasic and
things like that to correct for glasses
behind the cornea you have the iris the
colored part of the eye right your blue
eyes your brown eyes these are muscles
that help control the size of the pupil
which helps focus light even further
into the eye behind the iris you have
the lens this is the crystallin lens
when you're young it is clear it is
flexible and this is changed shape
because you have a muscle inside the eye
called the C body body and so you use
that muscle it changes the flexure of
this lens and then that controls your
ability to see far away and then you can
Flex it to see better up close things
like your smartphone now the challenge
is that as you get older this lens
begins to get thicker and it
crystallizes so by the time everybody's
in middle-age like 45 50 this lens gets
so kind of thick and hard kind of like a
marble that you can no longer Flex it
even though the Muscle Works spine you
can no longer Flex the lens and so you
have a hard time seeing up close so
people end up needing bifocals and
reading glasses and then if you wait
even longer than that you get older to
like 65 70 and above this lens begins to
become opaque it becomes cloudy like a
white or a yellow color and you can't
see through it and so we call that
having a cataract and so that's one of
the leading causes of blindness
worldwide thankfully there is cataract
surgery to fix that going Beyond further
deeper into the eye
you have the vitus humor this is the gel
that holds most of the shape of the eye
it's mostly water and type 2 collagen
but people often report having floaters
in their Vision right little spots that
drift around that is the collagen within
that vitous humor that is degrading and
sort of being suspended in what's left
and then on the very back part of the
eye you have the retina the retina is
the neurosensory tissue it is an
extension of your brain that has the
photo receptors that pick up light they
send that information through the
retinal ganglion cells through the optic
nerve into your brain so that your brain
can process vision and give you the
wonderful gift that is eyesight okay so
we got a bit of an idea on how cataracts
are formed as well as eye floaters but
we'll get to that one first let's
discuss cataracts does castor oil help
what have I found for castor oil and its
effect on cataracts interestingly
there's a lot of people and a lot of
things here on the internet where people
claim that as oil has helped them
improve or reverse their cataract
development I dug into this
unfortunately I could not find any
research to prove or disprove this
effect there just isn't anything on
there Honestly though thinking about the
pharmacokinetics of how castor oil would
have to get into the eye and get to that
part that structure of where the lens is
seems really unplausible because the
lens is a vascular right there's no
blood vessels getting to that lens
there's also so many barriers to the eye
that the castor oil would somehow have
to absorb through which is extremely
difficult even for a lot of medications
they have a hard time getting deep
inside the eye and so for you putting an
oil on the eye for it to get through the
structures get into the aquous humor
which is a fluid inside of the eye
that's generated kind of like the blood
the castor oil would have to somehow get
Upstream through that through that
aquous humor bathe the lens get through
the capsule of the lens it seems very
hard to believe that it would not only
prevent
cataracts but even reverse it like
trying to think of how the methods would
reverse the crystallization process that
occurs that leads to cataracts it just
seems um unplausible like Dr Allen I
looked for studies and there are none
there's one published case study it's
not peer-reviewed in one quasi Journal
called naturopathic doctor news and
review hardly really compelling evidence
so in short there's no scientific
evidence nor a compelling mechanism that
castor oil helps combat or even reverse
cataracts but what about something like
ey flers remember that's the collagen
pieces that Dr Allen mentioned before
what have I found on castor oil
and other eye conditions people online
also report castor oil as helping with
conditions further back in the eye like
helping with ey floaters again similar
to kind of what I did research in with
castor oil and cataracts could not find
anything in the published literature uh
for or against Castor oin effects on ey
floaters the kind of again same sort of
theory or methods of how cast oil could
get to the back of the eye again just
seems really unlikely what I think is
probably happening for both people who
are claiming it helped with their
cataracts or claiming that it helped
with her floaters is probably the fact
that castor oil again we know can help
stabilize the tear film and if you're
stabilizing the tear film and your dry
eye disease is improving the surface of
the eye may be healing and so light is
going to focus better inside the eye and
your eyesight may be sharper and so
people are perhaps correlating that
their eyesight is improving therefore
their diseases are going away and that
just may not be the case again I
completely agree in addition I surveyed
the vast land of PubMed where thousands
of studies are housed and found no
studies on Castor oil and eye floaters
but then why would we have ey drops with
castor oil in them if it doesn't seem to
have any scientific evidence for it well
scientists didn't add it to ey drops for
Giggles there is a reason so what have I
found in terms of castor oil and effects
on dry eye so as far as castor oil and
effects on dry eye you know we've known
that castor oil can have kind of a
moisturizing effect to the surface of
the eye in fact it's used in some eye
drops that are found over the counter
for dry eye it's even found in some
medications for dry eye the important
thing to note is that it's used at a
very dilute concentration like somewhere
around 2% and it's used used in these
formulations to either help stabilize
the tier film because you have oils in
your tier film to help prevent it from
evaporating and so it can sort of help
in that same way but also it's used in
some medications for dry eye not just to
help stabilize the tier fil but because
it holds tighter to the eye for longer
and that allows for medications to
penetrate into the eye give them more
time to actually penetrate and have an
effect one interesting research study
that was published in just 2021 in fact
didn't look at just dry eye they looked
more at blepharitis which is an
inflammation of the eyelids and by
applying 100% castor oil twice a day for
4 weeks they had significant
improvements in helping improve redness
some of the swelling it also helped with
some improvements in lid wiper
epitheliopathy which is something that
we see in dry eye where because the
surface is so dry the eyelids that are
going up and down they almost like
scratch on the surface of the ey and so
that was found to be improved in that
study okay Dr Allan is referencing this
study and exactly as mentioned this
randomized control trial indicated
improvement from 100% castro oil
Administration however it is critically
important the 100% castor oil was not
applied directly to the eye itself but
the skin around the eye using a
dedicated roller they applied castor oil
to one eye and nothing to the other eye
in addition to the fact that this was
not a double blind and did not include a
proper control the data indicated that
most of the measurements among the 25
plus measurements on ey Health the vast
majority showed no effect compared to
control the most impressive improvements
were also conveniently not compared
against control so taking all that into
consideration the evidence is still weak
that 100% castor oil is effective
however as Dr Allan mentioned and as has
been approved much lower concentrations
of castor oil are used in ey drops so is
there better evidence there the answer
is yes there are several studies but the
key difference is that they are using a
fraction of what's used in the previous
study that we just went over in the
neighborhood of just a few percent so
the takeaway here is it's a no-o on
Direct 100% castor oil application to
the eye it's probably not worth adding
100% castor oil even around the eye
especially when there's better methods
like eye drops that contain lower
concentrations and have better evidence
for them okay Dr Allen has one more
addition on why castor oil is sometimes
anecdotally believed to help the eyes
there's also the chance that I think if
somebody is using castor oil for health
benefits uh then they're also the same
type of person who's probably doing
other habits and lifestyle changes to
improve their health and that whatever
they may be doing could also be changing
their autonomic nervous system in a way
and your sympathetic and parasympathetic
nervous system helps control your pupil
size so perhaps there could be other
changes happening to the optical system
of the eye which could also explain
maybe subtle improvements in Vision ah
conf bounding factors the bane of
anecdote that many don't realize anyway
what's the overall takeaways here well
first off Dr Allen clearly knows his
stuff and puts out excellent eye related
information so his info will be linked
below for you to check out and pertinent
to the topic castor oil at 100%
concentration is highly unlikely to be
of much contribution to your eye health
or for air areas that it might have a
little evidence there are better
interventions in fact some of the
interventions like eye drops may even
have castor oil in them but at a much
lower concentration something bearable
for direct contact that said if you care
about your eye health I cover a
supplement that is known to have great
eye health benefits right here thanks
for tuning in